Finding Aid for Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research records, 1962-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research records 1962-2007
Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research.
9938 Bimu 2
Research consortium based at University of Michigan that acquires, preserves and disseminates computerized social science research data. ICPSR records include administrative files, grant files and documentation of the institute's educational activities. The research data files are maintained and serviced by ICPSR.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
21 linear feet
The record group was transferred by the unit beginning in July 1998 (donor no. 8741 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The ICPSR record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Box 21
The Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) is an organization of member institutions that provides access to the world's largest archive of computer-based and instructional data for the social sciences. Its primary purposes are to 1) acquire, develop, archive, and disseminate social science data and documentation, and 2) offer training in quantitative social analysis. ICPSR has over 325 members in the United States and Canada and serves hundreds of institutions in Europe, Oceania, Asia, and Latin America. Headquarters and central staff of ICPSR are located at the University of Michigan. Although originally conceived to meet the needs of political analysts, ICPSR serves a wide spectrum of social scientists, including economists, sociologists, psychologists, geographers, and historians, as well as other specialists in education, public health, social work, public administration, urban affairs, foreign policy, business administration, law, criminal justice, and gerontology.
The Inter-university Consortium for Political Research (ICPR) was founded in the summer of 1962 as a partnership between the Institute for Social Research (ISR) at the University of Michigan and twenty-one universities in the United States. Warren Miller, director of the Political Behavior Program of ISR, became director of the ICPR. ICPR addressed several current problems, including the increasing amounts of political science data collected by a variety of investigators and agencies, the duplication of effort gathering data, and the lack of availability of data to other researchers. One catalyst for cooperation was the development of computer technologies for rapid processing of large amounts of quantitative data. The first members affirmed the following four objectives:
(1) the development of data resources; (2) the establishment of a formal training program for graduate students and faculty; (3) the stimulation and facilitation of new research; and (4) the operation of a clearinghouse for the improved communication of information about ongoing research.
To implement its goals, a council of five representatives was chosen to work with the Survey Research Center (SRC). Furthermore, a summer program for faculty and graduate students was planned for 1963. A computer for data processing was acquired, and ICPR processed data and distributed code and analysis books for SRC studies and other accessions. ICPR also obtained funding to develop a major data repository. Finally, it planned publications to coordinate research and publicize ICPR.
Within the next decade, ICPR concentrated on increasing the number of collections in the data archives beyond SRC's survey data and building a technological infrastructure for storing, processing, and retrieving data. It also expanded professional research training and increased their membership. Advisory committees, composed of leading researchers from member institutions, were formed to develop subject-specific data archives for the repository, such as the Survey Research Archive and the Historical Archive. The staff at ICPR also increased to manage the data archives, input the raw data into machine-readable form, program the computers, provide hardware and software consultation, and furnish complex combinations or computations according to researchers' requests. As membership grew, membership structure was revised into categories based on facilities. Each member institution had one representative on a committee of representatives, which served to elect a council of ten.
In 1970, the Political Behavior Program of ISR became a center in its own right, known as the Center for Political Studies (CPS). ICPR was housed in CPS, although decisions were still made by the ICPR board. Warren Miller became director of CPS, and Richard Hofferbert later became head of ICPR. In 1975, Jerome Clubb assumed directorship of ICPR. At this time, the name was changed to Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) to reflect the increasingly multi-disciplinary focus of its resources. Under Clubb, data holdings were expanded in the fields of social and political history, international relations, quality of life, work patterns, historical and contemporary consumer attitudes, and the roles of women. ICPSR relied heavily on outside funding for augmenting existing data collections and building new ones. In addition, ICPSR provided networked access to its resources and accommodated microcomputers using data. Furthermore, the educational mission was broadened to include undergraduates. Membership reached over 240 institutions by 1979.
The 1980s saw new challenges and opportunities for ICPSR. ICPSR faced greater magnitudes of data with increasing complexity, changes in computing technology, and the institutional distribution of social scientists. Because many institutions lacked the software and hardware to manipulate new forms of data, ICPSR was well positioned to supply specific subsets of data in forms compatible with members' computing systems. To meet the increasing popularity of microcomputers, ICPSR concentrated resources on the development of exportable computing technologies. Indexing was also improved to help researchers identify consortium data remotely. Moreover, the development of the Consortium Data Network and the National Science Foundation Network enhanced transfer and dissemination of consortium data. By automating processing and documentation, converting documentation into machine-readable form, and providing on-line storage for documentation and data, ICPSR thereby eliminated the need for tapes and human management. Throughout these changes, ICPSR remained committed to instructing professionals and students in quantitative analysis methodologies in the context of social science research. ICPSR also continued to acquire, process, and disseminate data collections on a wide variety of topics, including the census, media polls, health, aging, election returns, and criminal justice. In 1989, ICPSR had over 340 member institutions.
In the 1990s under the leadership of Richard C. Rockwell, ICPSR continued to grapple with the rapidly changing technology environment. A foremost priority was the distribution of data sets to users' desktop computers, either through the Internet or CD-ROMs. Other paramount concerns were data migration and the adoption of lasting hardware and software standards. Nevertheless, ICPSR continued to emphasize its commitment to promote and facilitate research and instruction in the social sciences. They also underscored its purpose as a central data repository and dissemination service, and developed proactive acquisitions policies to respond to changes in the social sciences.
Because ISR administers the activities of the ICPSR, the researcher should also consult the records of ISR at the Bentley Historical Library. Current information about ICPSR, including council minutes, membership structure, the constitution, and mission statement, is available on its web site (as of 2007) at:
http://www.icpsr.umich.edu
Directors of the ICPSR
1962-1970 Warren Miller
1970-1971 Samuel H. Barnes (acting)
1971-1975 Richard Hofferbert
1975-1991 Jerome Clubb
1991-2000 Richard C. Rockwell
2000 Hal Winbourough (acting)
2000-2001 Erik Austin (acting)
2001- Myron Gutmann
The records of the Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research document the development, primary functions, and activities of the ICPSR. The records hold significance in documenting scientific cooperation among international research institutions. The records detail the history of technology, educational partnerships, computer-readable data sharing, and social science disciplines. The record group is divided into six series: Organization and Administration, Meetings, Individual Council Chairs' Papers, Resource Development and Services, Grants and Project Proposals, and Educational Activities.
Subjects:
Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research.; Social sciences--Research.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
- Organization and Administration
  The Organization and Administration series, (1962-2005, 6.0 linear feet) contains documentation from 1962 to 2005. The series is organized alphabetically. Organizational charts have been placed at the beginning of the series. Documentation of ICPSR committees is very strong, especially for earlier years. Included here is the 1962 "memorandum of organization." It served as the constitution. Various revisions of the memorandum of organization are contains here (1963, 1967, 1970, 1973, 1981, 1982). In 1991 a formal constitution and bylaws was created along with a memorandum of agreement between ICPSR and ISR. The advisory committee files mostly contain correspondence among scholars at various institutions who directed acquisition of data sets. These files document acquisition decisions and provide insight into the changing priorities of the data archives. Reports and surveys in these files show the status of the data archives at various points in time. Records of the Summer Program Advisory Committee complement materials in the separate Educational Activities series. Other committee files contain internal administrative records, including documentation of strategic planning decisions and revisions to the constitution and bylaws. Also included in this series are summary budget reports, and information about the membership structure.
  - Organizational Charts 1970, 1984, 1991, 1992, 1994-2006 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Group Minutes and Memoranda 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports (Filed with publications. See separate finding aid: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research publications) (Box 1)
  - Budget
    - 1967-1983, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986, 1988-1993 (Box 1)
    - Investment of ICPSR Funds (Box 1)
  - Collaboration with University of California-Berkeley 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Advisory Committees, General 1970-1983 (Box 1)
    - Alternate Data Media Committee 1991 (Box 1)
    - American Data Advisory Committee
      - General 1969-1973 (Box 1)
      - Acquisitions 1972-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Current Studies and Acquisitions 1969-1971 (Box 1)
      - Data Inventory Questionnaire and Responses 1969-1972 (Box 1)
      - Processing and Acquisitions Questionnaires and Analysis 1971-1972 (Box 1)
      - Sub-committee on Public Policy Data (Box 1)
    - Asian Historical Data Advisory Committee 1978 (Box 1)
    - Committee of Eight
      - Correspondence and Minutes 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Proposals 1963 (Box 1)
    - Collaborative Planning Group
      - Materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Readings (Box 1)
    - Comparative Politics Advisory Committee
      - General 1969-1973 (Box 1)
      - Acquisitions and Processing 1969-1973 (Box 1)
    - Computing and Technical Services Committee (Box 1)
    - Data Repository Committee 1964 (Box 1)
    - Development Plan Committee 1990 (Box 2)
    - Directors Review Committee 1998-1999, 2 folders (Box 21)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2029 ]
    - Economists Advisory Committee 1990 (Box 2)
    - Educational Activities Advisory Committee 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Finance Governance Personnel Committee 1990 (Box 2)
    - Future Planning Committee (Box 2)
    - Historical Archive Advisory Committee
      - Correspondence and Reports 1970-1977 (Box 2)
      - Meeting Minutes 1970, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Historical Data Advisory Committee (Box 2)
    - International Relations Archive Advisory Committee 1969-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Institutional Elites Data Advisory Committee 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - ISR External Review Committee (Box 2)
    - Long Range Planning (Box 2)
    - Mass Political Behavior Advisory Committee 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Negotiating Committee 1990 (includes Constitution and Bylaws) (Box 2)
    - Nominating Committee
      - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Nominations 1974-1991 (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - 1993 (Box 2)
      - 1997, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1999 (Box 2)
      - 2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Organizational Behavior Data Ad hoc Committee 1970-1973 (Box 2)
    - Planning Committee for Conferences on Machine Readable Records 1979, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Prime Advisory Committee 1987 (Box 2)
    - Programmatic Review Committee 1996 (Box 2)
    - Quantitative Data in History Committee 1971 (Box 2)
    - Review Committee 1988 (Box 2)
    - Social Science Archive Advisory Committee 1971-1975, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Summer Program Advisory Committee November 1995 (Box 3)
    - Social Science Research Council Committee on Archives for Quantitative Social Science Data 1965 (Box 3)
    - Social Science Research Council Committee on American Electoral Behavior 1961-1962 (Box 3)
    - Sociology Advisory Committee 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - State Data Committee 1966-1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Summer Program Advisory Committee
      - 1980-1981
        - Evaluations (Box 3)
        - Meeting Materials (Box 3)
      - 1982 (Box 3)
      - 1986, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Undergraduate Education Advisory Committee
      - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1980 Census Advisory Committee, 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1990 Census Advisory Committee, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Computer Personnel 1968 (Box 3)
  - Computing 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Bylaws and Memorandum of Organization
    - Memorandum of Organization
      - 1962 (Box 3)
      - 1963 (Box 3)
      - 1967 (Box 3)
      - 1970 (Box 3)
      - 1973 (Box 3)
      - 1981 (Box 3)
      - 1982 (Box 3)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 1995 (Box 3)
    - Constitution, Bylaws, and Memorandum of Agreement 1998 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Director of Archival Development, Erik Austin 1993 (Box 3)
    - Director Richard Rockwell 1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - ICPSR Council 1964-1998 (Box 3)
    - ICPSR Executive Directors 1964-2001, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Department of Justice Site Visit 1984 (Box 4)
  - Director Search 2000-2001
    - Applicants
      - Applicants, 6 folders (Box 21)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2031 ]
      - Finalists (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous Applicants (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous Reference Letters (Box 21)
      - Job Posting (Box 4)
  - Guide to Policies and Procedures, ISR (Box 4)
  - Guide to the Resources and Services of the Inter-university Consortium for Political Research 1970 (Box 4)
  - History of ICPSR (Box 4)
    (includes photos of staff and 2005 addition)
  - International Federation of Data Organizations (Box 4)
  - Job Posting-Senior Research Scientist (Box 4)
  - Letters of Agreement (Box 4)
  - Membership
    - Annual Dues 1967-1999 (Box 4)
    - Canada 1972-1978 (Box 4)
    - Categories and Fee Structure 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Category C Memberships 1976 (Box 4)
    - Easter and Central European Countries Information (Box 4)
    - Federated Membership in ICPR 1974 (Box 4)
    - Federated Membership Information 1977 (Box 4)
    - Historically Black Colleges 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - Justifications 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Mexican National Membership 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Multi-Institutional Membership 1971-1976 (Box 4)
    - Official Representative Change/Update Form (Box 4)
    - Trial and Subsidized Memberships 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Reports 1971-1992 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Surveys 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - University of Ljubljana, Slovenia (Box 4)
  - Official Representatives Survey 1975, 1988, 1997, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Prospectus for Consortium Development 1965 (Box 4)
  - Staff Memoranda 1968-1991 (Box 4)
  - Standard Practices Guide (Box 4)
- Meetings 1965-2007
  The Meetings series, (1965-2007, 8.0 linear feet) consists of materials from various types of governance meetings held by ICPSR from 1965 to 2007. Materials from Council, Official Representative, and other meetings included here, consist of agendas, lists of attendees, meeting minutes and background materials. The largest part of the series contains Council meeting materials. The Council is made up of twelve people elected by the ICPSR members, and tends to consist of scholars and data professionals. Six new Council members are elected every two years to serve four-year terms. The Council meetings are currently held three times annually, though in the earlier days of ICPSR they were held more frequently. The Council serves as the executive committee of the members and is authorized to act on their behalf in matters pertaining to budgetary, administrative, and organizational policies and procedures for ICPSR.
  Materials from the meetings of Official Representatives constitute the second-largest portion of this series. As a membership organization, each ICPSR member institution is represented by a locally designated "official representative." These Official Representatives ("ORs") met annually in Ann Arbor from 1963-1975, and then biennially from 1977 onward. (The 1972, 1974, and 1981 OR meetings were canceled). These meetings are intended to inform representatives about current ICPSR activities. In a letter from June 2004 (located in the donor file), Erik Austin described the value of the materials from these meetings in the following way: "Over the years, the ICPSR staff has 'pointed to' these periodic meetings of ORs as an opportunity to summarize present and future developments and activities of the ICPSR. Documents prepared for the periodic OR meetings, therefore, provide capsule summaries of the activities in which ICPSR has engaged, and the deliberations at these meetings condition policies and future directions that the organization has taken."
  - CPS Program Directors Meetings 1989-1992 (Box 5)
  - Council Meetings
    - Meeting Materials
      - 1965 (Box 5)
      - 1966, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1967, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - 1968, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - 1969, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - 1970, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - 1971, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - 1972, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - 1973, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - 1974, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - 1975, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - 1976, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1977, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1978, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1979, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1980, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1981, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1982, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1984, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1985, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1986, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1987, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1988, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1989, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1991, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1992, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1993, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1994, 6 folders (Box 7)
      - 1995, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - 1996, 6 folders (Box 8)
      - 1997, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - 1998, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - 1999, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - 2000, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - 2001, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - 2002, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - 2003, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 2004, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 2005, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 2006, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 2007 (Box 10)
    - Meeting Minutes (Box 11)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 11)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 11)
      - 1986 (Box 11)
      - 1987 (Box 11)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 11)
      - 1991-1993 (Box 11)
      - October 1993 (Box 11)
      - March 1995 (Box 11)
      - 1996, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - June 1997 (Box 11)
      - June 1998 (Box 11)
      - 2000, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Executive Session Meetings 1994 (Box 11)
  - Official Representatives Meetings
    - Meeting Materials
      - 1963 (Box 11)
      - 1964 (Box 11)
      - 1965 (Box 11)
      - 1966 (Box 11)
      - 1967 (Box 11)
      - 1968, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1969 (Box 11)
      - 1970 (Box 11)
      - 1971 (Box 11)
      - 1973 (Box 11)
      - 1975 (Box 11)
      - 1977 (Box 12)
      - 1979 (Box 12)
      - 1981 (Box 12)
      - 1983 (Box 12)
      - 1985 (Box 12)
      - 1987 (Box 12)
      - 1989 (Box 12)
      - 1991 (Box 12)
      - 1993 (Box 12)
      - 1995 (Box 12)
      - 1997, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - 1999 (Box 12)
      - 2001 (Box 12)
      - 2003 (Box 12)
      - 2005 (Box 12)
    - Planning Materials 2001, 2003 (Box 12)
  - Senior Staff Meetings
    - 1970-1971 (Box 12)
    - September 1994 (Box 12)
    - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - 2003-2004 (Box 12)
- Individual Council Chairs' Papers 1988-2002
  The Individual Council Chairs' Papers series (1988-2002, 1.0 linear feet) consists of materials from five former Chairs of the ICPSR Council (representing the time period from 1988 to 2002), which were solicited for the archives by Erik Austin, former Director of Archival Development. The papers document primarily the time period during which the individual served as Council Chair, but they also pertain to activities the individual may have participated in when serving as a regular council member, or in another capacity associated with the ICPSR. The contents of the collection vary from individual to individual, but contain primarily correspondence relating to various topics (notably, many of the Council Chairs' papers contain material on governance documents, such as the Memorandum of Agreement).
  - Karl Taeuber
    Karl E. Taeuber (Professor of Sociology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. Council member, 1986-1992; Council Chair:1988-1990; Chair of Development Plan Committee, 1990-1991; Chair of Advisory Committee on the 1990 Census, 1990-1997). The papers of Karl Taeuber, the earliest elected Council Chair in the collection, contain a large amount of "general papers," including correspondence, personal meeting notes, and reports.
    - Miscellaneous Papers, 4 folders (Box 13)
      (including information on Council nominations, budget, and governance)
    - Governance Documents (Constitution, Bylaws, etc.) 1989-1990 (Box 13)
    - Development Plan Committee 1990-1991 (Box 13)
    - Review Committee & Report 1989 (Box 13)
    - 1990 Census Advisory Committee, 1991 (Box 13)
  - William Flanigan
    William H. Flanigan (Professor, Department of Political Science, University of Minnesota. ICPSR Official Representative from the University of Minnesota, 1963-2000; Council member, 1968-1971, 1989-1995; Council Chair, 1992-1994). William Flanigan's papers reflect his early involvement with ICPR as an Official Representative for the University of Minnesota.
    - Correspondence
      - 1962-1967 (Box 13)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 13)
    - Evaluation of Richard Rockwell 1992, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Carole Shammas